Ted Koppel Collection
Ted Koppel Collection
1959-2008
Koppel, Ted, 1940 February 8-
350 linear feet; 28,500 computer files
Video of ABC News productions with Ted Koppel, including approximately 6,600 episodes of Nightline (Mar 1980-Nov 2005); video and audio media related to production of The Koppel Report; other video content related to Ted Koppel's career
3953664
Biographical History
Edward James Martin "Ted" Koppel (1940 February 8- ) is an English-born American broadcast journalist, television news anchor and author. He is most known for his twenty-five year tenure as anchor and managing editor of the ABC News program Nightline.
Ted Koppel was born on February 8, 1940 in the town of Nelson in Lancashire, England to German Jewish parents who had fled their home country just prior to the start of World War II. Koppel's father, Erwin Koppel, had owned a tire manufacturing company in Germany, and his mother, Alice Koppel, had been an amateur opera singer. The experience of the war in England and its immediate aftermath had an enduring impact on Koppel, and he has recounted in various contexts the influence the BBC radio rebroadcasts of Edward R. Murrow's war reporting had on his early ambitions to pursue a career in journalism. From 1951-1953, Koppel attended the Abbotsholme School in Staffordshire, England, spending summers and vacations with his parents in Frankfurt, Germany. In 1953, Koppel emigrated with his parents to the U.S.
At the age of sixteen, Ted Koppel enrolled at Syracuse University to pursue a major in Speech and Political Science. During his four years at Syracuse University (1956-1960), Koppel was active as an announcer/disc jockey at the University's radio station WAER and served as the station's Program Director during his senior year (1959-1960). During his final year at Syracuse, Koppel broadcast a self-produced radio report, This is Moscow, comprised of interview clips and commentary collected on a summer trip to Moscow on the occasion of the American Exhibition there. After earning his Bachelor of Science degree from Syracuse University, Koppel attended graduate school at Stanford University studying Mass Communications and Political Science (1960-1962). He was awarded a Master of Arts degree in 1962 with the submission of his graduate thesis, Attitudinal and informational changes precipitated by local newspaper coverage of the Eichmann trial. While at Stanford, Koppel met his future wife Grace Anne Dorney. They were married in 1963, the same year that Koppel became a naturalized U.S. citizen.
After graduation from Stanford, Koppel served a short internship at the NBC network before landing his first job as a copyboy for WMCA radio in New York. A year later, Koppel was hired on at ABC News radio along with Stewart Klein, Charlie Osgood, Betty Adams, Howard Hodkins and former WMCA disc jockey Jim Harriott to staff a new daily news program, Flair Reports. Koppel had only been at ABC News a few months when President John F. Kennedy was assassinated, and one of his first on-air assignments was to stake out the Vice President's residence to solicit comments from Lyndon Johnson. In 1965, Koppel spent several weeks in Selma, Alabama covering the fallout from the Edmund Pettus Bridge incident and the civil rights marches that followed.
Koppel made the shift from radio to television in 1966 when ABC News recruited him to cover the Vietnam War as a foreign television correspondent (1966-1967). While in Vietnam, Koppel produced regular reports for the ABC evening news. In 1968, Koppel returned to the U.S. to cover the Nixon presidential campaign and to serve as Miami Bureau Chief covering Latin American and Cuban affairs. The following year, Koppel was back covering the Vietnam War as Southeast Asia Bureau Chief stationed in Hong Kong (1968-1971). In 1971, Koppel began his first stint as ABC's Chief Diplomatic Correspondent covering Secretary of State William P. Rogers, and then Secretary of State Henry Kissinger through the Watergate years. In this post, Koppel did extensive reporting on China, including traveling with President Nixon on his historic visit to China in 1972. In 1974, Koppel traveled with Henry Kissinger on his shuttle-diplomacy efforts in the Middle East. From 1975-1977, Koppel served as anchor for The ABC Saturday Night News. During a brief hiatus in 1976 while his wife attended law school, Koppel produced daily ABC radio commentaries while collaborating with Marvin Kalb on a novel on Middle East affairs, In the National Interest. In 1978, Koppel produced Second to None, a ground-breaking eleven-part report about US-Soviet military preparedness. That year also saw Koppel return for his second stint covering the State Department (1978-1980).
As Chief Diplomatic Correspondent covering the Carter State Department in late-1979, Koppel was a key figure in ABC's nightly coverage of the ongoing Iran hostage crisis, America Held Hostage (first aired November 8, 1979). In addition to his regular State Department reports, Koppel frequently served as a substitute anchor for the program, periodically relieving Frank Reynolds behind the anchor desk. It was largely the impression he made in this role that influenced then president of ABC News Roone Arledge to select Koppel as the founding anchor for the new late-night news program, Nightline (first aired March 24, 1980). Evolving out of the Iran hostage update program, Nightline grew rapidly into a cornerstone of the network's expanding roster of television news programs. For nearly three decades from its inception (1980 -2005), Ted Koppel anchored the innovative late-night show that featured a unique mix of in-depth reporting, extended live interviews (often with multiple participants), and live updates on breaking news stories. In the era before the emergence of the 24 hour cable news cycle, Nightline was often the only conduit for breaking-news between the evening and morning news reports. In addition to creating the mold for the modern televisions news magazine program, Nightline has contributed important innovations to the practice of television journalism including the use of simultaneous live satellite interviews with multiple participants; the use "natural sound" narration (the "Petacque" technique); the town-meeting discussion/debate format; and the use of Hi8 and hand-held video cameras for the collection of original news footage.
In 1987, at the height of Nightline's initial success, Koppel entered into contract negotiations with the ABC network and its parent company at that time, Capital Cities Communications. Part of these negotiations focused on Koppel's desire to establish his own production company, and in March of 1988 ABC News finalized an agreement to assist in the formation of Koppel's new venture, Koppel Communications Inc. (KCI). ABC agreed to air several KCI-produced news specials and documentaries each year (The Koppel Report), as well as allowing Koppel to produce additional programs for independent distribution through other outlets. Such a deal was virtually unprecedented at its time for a network news figure. The Koppel Report, anchored by Ted Koppel and featuring the production talents of a number of his Nightline colleagues, was an award-winning program that saw the production of 11 news programs over three years (1988-1990). Typically in a documentary format, though also including town hall debates, the programs explored in-depth many of the major events of the day. Programs included examinations of the televangelist phenomenon (The Billion Dollar Pie), life in the Soviet Union at the end of the Cold War (Sex in the Soviet Union), the events of the Romanian Revolution (Death of a Dictator), and the Tiananmen Square uprising in Beijing (Tragedy at Tiananmen: The Untold Story).
In 2005, after twenty-five years and with nearly 6,600 episodes under his belt, Ted Koppel decided to move on from his role as anchor and managing editor on Nightline. His last program aired November 22, 2005. Shortly after leaving ABC News, Koppel, former Nightline Executive Producer Tom Bettag, and a group of eight other former Nightline staffers formed a deal with the Discovery Channel to produce a series of news programs and documentaries for cable television. The subsequent Koppel on Discovery (2006-2008) productions included: The Price of Security; Iran: Most Dangerous Nation; Our Children's Children's War; Living with Cancer; Breaking Point; The Last Lynching; and a much acclaimed four-part series on China, The People's Republic of Capitalism. This in-depth exploration of the modern Chinese economy has been singled-out by Koppel as one of his most satisfying documentary achievements.
After 2008, Koppel remained active as a broadcaster, author and speaker, serving as a news analyst for National Public Radio, a contributor to BBC America, and a correspondent for the NBC News program Rock Center with Brian Williams. In addition, Koppel has contributed articles to numerous books and publications, including Forbes, The New York Times and The Wall Street Journal.
In addition to his voluminous broadcast work, Koppel has accumulated a number of writing credits as well. Some of his written works include: In the National Interest (1977, with Marvin Kalb); Nightline: History in the Making and the Making of Television (1996, with Kyle Gibson); Live from the Trenches: The Changing Role of the Television News Correspondent (1998, contributor); Off Camera: Private Thoughts Made Public (2000); Lights Out: A Cyberattack, A Nation Unprepared, Surviving the Aftermath (2015).
Ted Koppel has received numerous awards and recognitions over the course of his long career including: the Edward R. Murrow Lifetime Achievement Award, 41 Emmy awards, eight George Foster Peabody Awards, 10 duPont-Columbia Awards, 10 Overseas Press Club Awards, two George Polk Awards, and 2 Sigma Delta Chi Awards. Koppel was awarded the first Gold Baton (duPont-Columbia Awards) for Nightline's week-long series originating from South Africa, the Gabriel Personal-Achievement Award from the National Catholic Association of Broadcasters and Communicators, and selection as a Chevalier de l'Ordre des Arts et des Lettres from the Republic of France. He has received more than 20 honorary degrees from universities in the United States.
[In addition to the material in the Ted Koppel Collection, the following sources were consulted for this biography: Nightline: History in the Making and the Making of Television (Random House, 1996); Off Camera: Private Thoughts Made Public (Vintage, 2001); The House That Roone Built (Little, Brown, 1994); Ted Koppel interview video (conducted by Don Carleton 6/14/2005), Archive of American Television, accessed 10/05/2015 (http://www.emmytvlegends.org/interviews/people/ted-koppel#); Ted Koppel Wikipedia page, accessed 10/08/2015 (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ted_Koppel).]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ted Koppel Collection contains over 9,000 media items in videotape, audio tape and optical disc formats, as well as over 22,500 digital archival preservation copies of Nightline episodes, The Koppel Report, and other Koppel related content (7,500 archival masters in duplicate and 7,500 viewing copies). The collection also includes over 6,000 Nightline transcripts in digital form.
The vast majority of the collection consists of a comprehensive run of the Nightline program during Ted Koppel's tenure as anchor, 1980-2005. There are approximately 6,600 episodes of Nightline represented in the collection. Virtually all of these episodes are available in digital format, most with accompanying digital text transcripts. Years covered include: 1980, 1981, 1982, 1983, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988, 1989, 1990, 1991, 1992, 1993, 1994, 1995, 1996, 1997, 1998, 1999, 2000, 2001, 2002, 2003, 2004, 2005
The collection also contains several thousand video and audio recordings related to The Koppel Report and other Koppel Communications Inc. productions, including original interviews, field recordings, production materials and broacast masters. The collection contains material related to all eleven episodes of The Koppel Report: The Billion Dollar Pie; The Blue X Conspiracy; DC/Divided City; Death of a Dictator; Drugs, Crime and Doing Time; The Legalization of Drugs/A National Town Meeting: The Legalization of Drugs; News from Earth; Sex in the Soviet Union; Television: Revolution in a Box; A Town Meeting with Nelson Mandela; Tragedy at Tiananmen: The Untold Story.
The collection also includes examples of Ted Koppel's work for the Discovery Networks, Koppel on Discovery, as well as additional ABC News programs and specials including: Viewpoint, Up Close, Nightline in Primetime, and the Jennings Koppel Report. There is additional miscellaneous material related to Ted Koppel interviews, promotional spots and appearance clips. There is also a small sample of Ted Koppel's radio work while a student at Syracuse University and Stanford University, including the report This is Moscow.
Other Formats Available
Much (but not all) of the collection has been digitized, and transcripts are available for many (but not all) episodes. More information on available formats in given in the appropriate sections of the inventory below.
Arrangement of the Collection
Media is grouped by series and episode. Nightline, Viewpoint and Up Close episodes are listed in chronological order.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Radio, television, film; Koppel, Ted, 1940 February 8-; ABC News.; Discovery Communications, Inc.; Koppel Communications, Inc.; Koppel on Discovery (Television program); Koppel report (Television program); Nightline (Television program); Nightline upclose (Television program); Viewpoint (Television program); Broadcast journalism.; Cold War.; Documentary television programs.; History, Modern -- 20th century.; Interviews.; Nonfiction television programs.; Television broadcasting of news -- United States.; Television journalists -- United States.; Television news anchors -- United States.; Television news programs.; United States -- History -- 20th century.; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century.; United States -- Social life and customs -- 20th century.; World politics -- 20th century.; War correspondents -- United States.; Audiotapes.; Digital audio formats.; Digital moving image formats.; Optical discs.; Transcripts.; Videotapes.; Television journalists.; Television news anchors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Digitized media may be accessed at a viewing station in the SCRC reading room.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ted Koppel, 2011.
Inventory
- Koppel on Discovery, 2006-2008
  After leaving Nightline in November of 2005, Koppel, Nightline Executive Producer Tom Bettag, and a group of eight other Nightline staffers formalized an agreement with Discovery Networks to produce a series of documentaries and other long-form news programs. Over the course of nearly three years, Koppel and company delivered seven documentaries, including a much acclaimed four-part series on China, "The People's Republic of Capitalism". This in-depth exploration of the modern Chinese economy has been singled-out by Koppel as one of his most satisfying documentary achievements. Other Koppel on Discovery programs include: "The Price of Security"; "Iran: Most Dangerous Nation"; "Our Children's Children's War"; "Living with Cancer"; "Breaking Point"; and "The Last Lynching".
  The Ted Koppel Collection contains a few dozen VHS tapes related to two separate Koppel on Discovery documentaries: The Price of Security and The People's Republic of Capitalism. Most of these tapes are post-production rough-cuts, or "screeners", of the four-part China documentary.
  - People's Republic of Capitalism, Parts 1-4, aired 07/09/2008-07/12/2008
    Executive Producer: Tom Bettag; Producers: John Alexander, James Blue, Peter Demchuk, Jay Lamonica, Nick Mackie, Elissa Rubin, Alissa Shapiro, Emily Stanitz; Managing Editor: Ted Koppel; Production: The Discovery Channel.
    Episodes of the four-part series are: Part 1: Joined at the Hip; Part 2: MAO-ism to ME-ism; Part 3: The Fast Lane; Part 4: It's the Economy Stupid.
    The collection contains approximately 26 VHS tapes of various post-production versions of each episode including rough cuts. Most tapes contain 1-2 acts of a particular episode, and there is some duplication.
    - Autos (Act 4.8 and Act 5.6), 03/17/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02559 (Box 59)
    - Autos (Act 4.11), 03/18/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02560 (Box 59)
    - Autos (Acts 1.8, 2.7.2, 3.6.2, 4.11.1, 5.7), 03/25/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02561 (Box 59)
    - Autos (Acts 1.10), 03/31/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02562 (Box 59)
    - Autos (Act 2.10), 04/01/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02563 (Box 59)
    - Autos (Act 3.8.1 and Act 4.9-2), 04/02/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02564 (Box 59)
    - Autos (Act 5.9), 04/03/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02565 (Box 59)
    - Autos, 05/06/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02566 (Box 59)
      digital video available
    - Babel (Act 1-5), 11/27/2007; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02567 (Box 59)
    - Babel (Acts 1, 2 and 3), 12/10/2007; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02568 (Box 59)
    - Babel (Acts 4, 5 and 6), 12/10/2007; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02569 (Box 59)
    - Babel (Act 1.8), 03/20/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02570 (Box 59)
    - Babel, 05/07/2008; cassette damaged: tape gate broken off.; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02571 (Box 59)
    - Economy (4.0) (Coal), 03/12/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02572 (Box 59)
    - Economy (Act 2) (1st cut) ("particularly rough"), 03/12/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02573 (Box 59)
    - Economy (Act 2.1) ("very rough cut"), 03/13/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02574 (Box 59)
    - Economy Stringout (Edit 14), 05/08/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02575 (Box 59)
    - Economy, 05/07/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02576 (Box 67)
    - Economy (Act 2.0) (7:55), 03/19/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02577 (Box 67)
    - Values (Acts 1-5), 03/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02578 (Box 67)
    - Values (Act 3) (KTV option), 04/03/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02579 (Box 67)
    - Values (Acts 2 and 3), 03/12/2008; tape w/o case; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02580 (Box 67)
    - Values (Act 3) (expanded KTV), 03/13/2008; tape w/o case; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02581 (Box 67)
    - Values (Acts 3, 4 and 5), 03/19/2008; tape w/o case; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02582 (Box 67)
    - Values (Act 1), 03/26/2008; tape w/o case; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02583 (Box 75)
    - Values (Act 2 and Act 3) (KTV), 03/31/2008; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:10:00; koppel_02584 (Box 75)
  - Price of Security, aired 09/10/2006
    Executive Producer: Tom Bettag; Producers: James Blue, Peter Demchuk, Richard Harris, Jay Lamonica, Elissa Rubin; Managing Editor: Ted Koppel; Production: Koppel Communications Inc., The Discovery Channel.
    This post-9/11 examination of national security policy was Koppel's fist documentary production for Discovery. An original 90 minute documentary was followed by an additional 90 minute town hall segment. Issues such as airport security, detention policy, torture, Guantanamo Bay, NSA mass surveillance are examined in light of the tension between security needs and individual liberties.
    The collection contains VHS copies of the documentary portion of the broadcast only. The subsequent town hall debate segment is not included.
    - The Price of Security (without Act 8), 05/04/1990; Videotape, VHS, dub, 0:40:00; koppel_02556 (Box 59)
    - The Price of Security (73:45) (905111DCI), 09/09/2006; Videotape, VHS, dub, 1:14:00; koppel_02557 (Box 59)
- The Koppel Report, 1988-1990
  This award-winning program, anchored by Ted Koppel and featuring the production talents of a number of Nightline veterans, included eleven episodes over three-years covering such diverse topics as television, religion, human sexuality, crime and punishment, technology, and international politics. Typically in a documentary format, though at times including town hall debates, The Koppel Report explored in-depth many of the major events of the day, and in the process documented not only the primary historical record of events, but also reflected how those events were perceived and contextualized as they happened.
  In addition to the Koppel Communications Inc. owned broadcast masters of each report, the collection also contains hundreds of hours of accumulated source video that was utilized in the making of each program. This material includes unedited original footage of complete interviews, field footage of important places and developing events, clip reels of relevant news footage and historical footage, documentaries and original performance material, as well as post-production elements (graphics, effects and audio tracks) and submaster versions of episodes and episode segments.
  The collection contains material related to all eleven episodes of The Koppel Report: The Billion Dollar Pie; The Blue X Conspiracy; DC/Divided City; Death of a Dictator; Drugs, Crime and Doing Time; The Legalization of Drugs/A National Town Meeting: The Legalization of Drugs; News from Earth; Sex in the Soviet Union; Television: Revolution in a Box; A Town Meeting with Nelson Mandela; Tragedy at Tiananmen: The Untold Story.
  A large portion of The Koppel Report videotape materials have been digitized (including the final broadcast masters). These items are noted in the inventory below.
  - The Billion Dollar Pie, aired 05/12/1988
    Executive Producer: Richard N. Kaplan; Directors: Roger Goodman, Jan Rifkinson; Production: Koppel Communications Inc.
    This program explores the phenomenon of Christian television evangelism. The opening segment establishes a contrast between small, grass roots congregations, like the Reverend John Sherfy's congregation, and the large, lucrative ministries of the most popular "televangelists". The decline of religious broadcasting is attributed to the shrinking demographic that has traditionally provided the bulk of the funding (through religious donations) and the proliferation of sexual misconduct scandals, infighting among the ministries and financial corruption. The bulk of the program centers on a town-hall-style panel discussion from the Central Church in Memphis, Tennessee. The discussion focuses on topics such as the corrupting force of big-money on religious broadcasters and Christian ministry in general, the limited growth potential of the audience for religious broadcasting, the impact of high-profile scandals on the biggest television ministries, and the destructive affects of intensive competition among the ministries for a diminishing slice of the revenue pie.
    Total media holdings related to this program include approximately 150 items (about 100 hours). The majority of this consists of original footage of churches, church services and interviews with preachers and congregants. The collection also includes clip compilations and dubs of various televangelist productions, as well as the complete original recordings of the televangelist studio debate filmed in Memphis. In addition to a batch of post-production material, there are multiple versions of the final show, including two broadcast masters.